experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening. Welcome back to the Lord of Spirits
podcast, everyone.
My co-host, Father Stephen D. Young
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana
and I am Father Andrew Stephen Damick
in Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
And if you're listening to us live,
you can call in at 855 AF radio.
That's 855-237-2346.
And Montesca Trudy will be taking your calls tonight,
which we will get to in the
second part of our show. So tonight we begin a four-part series, that's right, four-part
series on the Christology of the Old Testament. And first we're going to be talking about the
Angel of the Lord. The Angel of the Lord has mentioned dozens of times in the Holy Scriptures,
yet the identity and nature of this figure remains kind of fuzzy for a lot of Christians. Is he an
angel like one of the heavenly hosts is he a symbol of Jesus?
Christ, is he the son of God himself?
Does he have a body?
Is this figure compatible with trinitarian theology?
So if you've ever wanted to take a really thorough look
through the scriptures to understand
what this phrase means and who this is,
stick with us tonight.
So let's start by looking at the words themselves.
So Father Stephen, where does this phrase,
the angel of the Lord come from linguistically,
like the actual words, Hebrew?
Well, there we go.
Good night everybody. Yeah. So also I just want to say if you've never wanted to take a really thorough look through the scriptures to understand who the angel of the Lord is, you should also stay. Yes, please.
Because there will be dad jokes and other stuff that might entertain you.
Yeah. And also I hear by guarantee now that this episode will be 97% less horrifying than the last one. Yeah. Right.
Yeah, we had a number of people contact us about the last
episode, the Monster Menu episode and say that they actually were experiencing nightmares afterwards
despite the parental advisory that I gave at the beginning of the episode.
Yes, that we reiterated repeatedly.
In writing, yes.
Yeah.
Our content warning.
But so yeah, to dig into a little more, when we talk about
the angel of the Lord, right, Lord here is of course standing in as the English translation of
of Yahweh.
So we're talking about the angel of Yahweh, the God of Israel.
And so there's a bunch of different pieces to that.
I think the first piece, we'll do it word by word.
So the first word is the, right?
And it's important that we're talking about the angel of the Lord, right?
The angel of Yahweh, the definite article is it where it's right.
that there are
There are a bunches of places in, there's a talk about,
in Angel of the Lord, right, without a definite article.
An example of that is in Matthew 1 verse 20,
where it's told that in Angel of the Lord comes to St. Joseph the Betroath
to tell him about the conception of Christ and that it's of the Holy Spirit.
spirit and someone out there maybe about to say well you have it in verse 24
it says the angel of the Lord, right? But the Greek article is not a definite article.
Yeah, right. It's more of a demonstrative like this or that angel, that angel, you know,
that's referring back to say the same one, right? The same one that was mentioned before. That's the
anophoric use of the Greek article for the language nerds out there.
So yeah, but it Hebrew the Ha prefix.
right in Ha Malak, Yahweh, is a real live definite article. Right. We talked about this
before when we talked about the Satan in the book of Job. Right. Right. Right. So this
is indicating a particular, a very particular being, not just a good angel or an angel that
is loyal to Yahweh or serves Yahweh. There's lots of those, right? But this is one particular.
the angel. Yeah. Yeah. So then the next word is angel. Right. Right. And that comes of course
from, you know, the English word angel mind you comes from the Greek angulose, which simply
means messenger. Like that's really all that the word itself just means. I mean, there's
we tend to think of it as a species, but it really is the name of a job. Angulose, a messenger.
You know, because you've got it because it comes from
that word that means news.
You know, so it's someone who delivers news
is what the word means, anglos.
Right.
And the Hebrew word behind that also means messenger.
The Hebrew word that's used, mall, ock,
also refers to a messenger or an angel
in the spiritual sense.
And using it in that spiritual sense, by the way,
is not confined to the Hebrew scriptures.
that term is used for the sort of lower level spirits
that serve pagan gods like in,
in Ugritic Epic poetry.
It's fairly common, we use that in that regard.
You can find in a lot of Semitic religious stuff,
you know, even that's current in the Middle East.
Like, I think it's either the Yazidis
or one of those religious groups there
that there's a lot of discussion about.
Malik, you know, as an angel term.
Yeah, yeah.
So, um, and yeah, as you mentioned it, as we talked about back when we went through the ranks of angels, right, these aren't species.
These are roles.
These are job descriptions, right, the different ranks.
It's what they do, what their service, uh, to God is about.
Right.
And that's in part because angels don't reproduce after their
kind the way people and animals and plants do.
Right.
So kind of what species, that's the actual boundary of species.
Is this sort of reproductive sense?
Right.
And so that means that each angel is in a sense, sweet generous, right?
Each one is its own genera, right?
It doesn't go to species.
Right.
So it's its own type of thing.
So all that tells us right
off the bat is that the angel of the Lord, this particular being, is a spiritual being
of some kind, right? That's really all that sort of tells us who at least one of this
being's functions is to convey messages from the divine realm.
Then we get to of the...
How great!
Is this too granular? No, because yeah, no, you should see why dissertation. Yeah, this isn't this isn't the show where that question is ever really
applicable. Yeah, yeah.
But so I mean, if you think about of in English, right, can mean a whole lot of things. Right. Yeah, right. It can mean possessive. It can just mean associated with it can mean.
I mean, yeah, yeah, just constituent.
So you could say like, you know, this is, you know,
the mug of Father Stephen, right?
It's like possession, or you could say,
this is a mug of coffee.
That doesn't mean coffee owns the mug, right?
It's talking about what is in the mug, right?
So, oh, it's very versatile.
And so, it gets used as a punt all the time
in Bible translation.
Right, because there are a lot of complex constructions,
so like the Greek genitive, this is for the nerds again.
And in Hebrew often, there's just sort of
of an attributed position where
just to put two nouns sort of next to each other. Right. And by placing them in those positions,
they are related to each other. And there's all kinds of nuance in determining exactly how they're
related. And if you're translating and you don't want to weigh in and take a strong position,
you could just put like, of, right, let the reader try to figure out of in what sense.
So there are at least
two senses of of the in this case or of really because you know it's Yahweh not the Lord technically but
So there's two senses of of at least that are valid so one of those is that possessive sense because there are places
in the Old Testament where Yahweh the God of Israel
refers to the angel of the Lord as my angel
Alright, so...
That's clearly a possessive.
So reading it as Yahweh's angel,
that's one valid way to read it.
But it's also valid to read it
as almost like an attributive adjective
so that it's would be something like
this is the Yahweh angel, right?
Or the Lord angel.
Yeah, right.
And so that is a, well what would that mean?
Well that gets...
developed in second temple literature. There's a lot of literature in the second
temple period, so this is between about 500 BC and 70 AD, that there is a figure,
this sort of angelic figure, this prominent angelic figure who in some texts,
like the apocalypse of Abraham is called Yeho-El.
Which means this is an angel
whose name is Yahweh God.
Right. So it's an angel, but it's named God's name.
So that's a development of this reading of the Yahweh angel.
And as we go through tonight and look at these different passages and different
texts in the Old Testament where the angel of the Lord appears, I think some of
why this is where such a odd sounding guy.
idea would come from will become more obvious.
Yeah, yeah, because I mean, like I said, this phrase gets used in piles and piles of places.
And we're going to look at probably most of them, I think.
But if you look at them, then you, then a picture emerges.
I think that's the important thing.
You know, once you realize that these are all referencing one figure,
then it becomes much clearer.
and you have to as we
talked about very early on in the first couple podcasts, you'd have to get out of your
head the idea that ancient Jewish folks and ancient Israelites were unitary and monotheists,
right?
That they were monotheists at all and that they saw that God was only one person.
Because if you have that in your head, then finding out that they believed there was an angel
named Yahweh God, there's no way to put that together.
right it doesn't doesn't
work, right? And so we're going to see how much that doesn't work in the Old Testament. And
so that is again, that is a modern thing based partially in rabbinic Judaism and partially
in 19th century German idealism, right? Red back into ancient Israel and ancient Judaism.
So a bunch of people just marked their bingo cards as we said that.
We should put out Lord of Spirits being a card.
an idea. Right now there's a fan making one right now. And we'll complete the system of German idealism.
But the
Fick to couldn't do it. Anyway. So there, that is to say, there is this idea of that this the angel of the
Lord figure represents not just an angel or a special angel but an especially divine figure.
And that then also gets attached in various places.
A lot of places in Second Temple literature,
but one place we're about to talk about
in the Old Testament itself,
that gets then attached to traditions about the Messiah.
Yeah, right.
And that includes in Isaiah chapter nine.
Right, and so I mean, this verse,
it's Isaiah nine, six or nine, five,
depending on whether you're reading a translation
the Hebrew, the Greek. And this is one that a lot of people know because, you know, you
hear this around Christmas typically. And I think that this is, you know, this is very
memorably used as a lyrics to the Messiah by Handel, right? So, you know, it goes like
this for two us, a child is born, two us, a son is given, and the government shall be
upon his shoulder, and his name shall be called. And here's where there's a little bit of
variation. Wonderful counselor.
That's what it says in the Hebrew, or angel of great counsel.
That's what it says in the Greek.
Mighty God everlasting father, Prince of Peace.
So that's interesting.
They're not quite the same.
The Greek is clearly not simply translating that Hebrew, although as you probably, I think
you've remarked in the past, that it seems that the Greek Old Testament in a lot of ways
seems to have been transiting a different, slightly different
You're not going to be able to do that.
of tradition than what we know of in extant Hebrew stuff in a lot of ways. And this would
seem to be one of those instances where it's not exactly the same phrase.
Yeah. And there's a way to get from one to the other, but we'll talk about that a little
later. Yeah, sure. Right. So they could bected to the angel of the Lord and the word wonderful.
Or they're translated here as wonderful. Yeah. Yeah. Wonderful counselor. Although sometimes
And you see that as one...
beautiful comma counselor, yeah, which in Hebrew there's no
commas. Yeah, there's no fluctuation at all. So yeah, yeah.
And so yeah, I'm, so the Hebrew is, I'm going to mispronounce this,
but Pele, or something like that. And then the Greek is
Megalis, Voulis, Angelos, which, you know, for people who know
a little bit of Greek, that's pretty clearly the great council
Angel, Megalys, Voulis, Angelo's.
So yeah, that's that's what it says there in Isaiah chapter nine. Yeah, and send your pronunciation hate mail to father
Andrew Damick. Yeah, which we do.
Occasionally. Yeah, we do. We do mostly about how you say Lafayette Louisiana though, but true.
You just can't do that. Ah, you just don't like it. I'm
From there. Yeah
so so yeah, so this this idea
Yeah.
of this adjoke being there, you see this is listed here
within these messianic titles, right?
Clearly in the Greek, and I think in a kind of sideways way,
even in the Hebrew, like there's a place
the Greek is getting at.
And the way it's expressed there is the angel of great council.
Now to be clear, this is COUNSEL.
Yeah, right.
not council like the divine council.
Yeah, it'd be neat if it was the other one, but it is COUNSEL, like my other podcast.
Yes, the whole council, like God.
So this is connecting that angel of the Lord figured not only to the Messiah but also to
This idea of the council, the deliberations, right, the will, the expression of will.
the will of God. So even though it is COUNSEL that is not unrelated to the divine council CIL,
the council CIL is aware those deliberations and those things take place that are then announced
Right? By the by the messenger right by the angel and
So that piece of the angel of the Lord tradition
is actually one that's referenced a lot both inside the New Testament and
outside the Scriptures, but it's done in this kind of sub-roso way where people
don't necessarily notice it. I think I'm gloss over it because it requires
either paying a lot of attention to detail in the New Testament or reading a lot of
stuff that nobody but me ever reads.
outside of the New Testament, right? So not a lot of folks.
Or all the people in our Facebook group were constantly asking for a list of those books
that you can read at home. Yes. Yes. Well, they do buy them. Kudos to you guys. But if
they're honest, how many have read how much of them, right? Hey, don't call me out,
Yeah, I'm working on it. It's true. Yeah. Yeah.
our shelves will speak out against us on the day of judgment.
But so that and that tradition, the way that tradition shows up most obviously in the
New Testament is in references to the Torah being given by or through angels.
Yeah, right, which is I mean, it's one of those things that's said very clearly in the Bible,
but I think a lot of people just walk right.
like you said, it's a detail that unless you notice these kinds of details, it may not register.
And that's especially because there's no place in the Bible where it sort of really lays it all out.
And where you might expect it, if you're looking for the Bible to be some kind of textbook,
you know, they're in Exodus, it's not said there. It's not said, you know, that angels gave the Torah
Tomozus, but it's referenced later. So like, act 753 where you've got
St. Stephen, right, you know, just as he's about to be stoned, right?
He says to the leaders of the Jews that they, he says,
you who received the law as delivered by angels and did not keep it.
That's X 753.
So, I mean, it's right there in the Bible.
Like, you don't even have to go to a second temple literature to get this
or patricic sources or whatever.
It's right there.
Right.
Right?
And down.
notice there, you know, they're angry and they stone him to death. But none of them say,
what are you talking about? Yeah, right.
Here. And there's actually that St.
Stevens sermon there. His final sermon in Acts 7 is full, actually, of these little tidbits.
This is just one of them. All right. These pieces of second temple tradition and things
that he and all of the people listening to him had just received. Right. Right. As
part of their religion, part of their way of life, part of their practice, and they didn't
sit there and distinguish. Well, that's just a tradition I heard, right? You know, this
is what's actually in the Bible, and then, oh, here's this other, they don't make that distinction.
Yeah, that's another thing. And, you know, St. Stephen went to school with St. Paul, with
Rabbi Gimellial, and you see St. Paul do the same thing all the time, just referencing these
things as if they were right.
there in the Old Testament and they're not in the Old Testament. In the actual text that most
of us would consider canon at least. And there's a there's a similar reference, speaking of St. Paul,
there's a similar reference in Hebrews 2 verse 2. Yeah, yeah. So this is another one where he says,
for since the message declared by angels proved to be reliable, and every transgression or disobedience
received a just retribution. So I mean it's this you know, dependent clause. And then you know,
the next thing he says is how shall we escape if we neglect so great a salvation? He's making a
contrast. He's saying if this is this serious, then boy, you know, now that salvation's come,
what are you going to do if you neglect that? But yeah, this message declared by angels proved to
to be reliable, namely the Law of Moses.
Right.
And if you're going to use that,
you could...
instruction rhetorically, right, if A, then B, to try to prove B, then your audience has to all accept A. Yeah, A is assumed, right? So that means again, all the readers, all the hearers, right?
Hebrews are just expected to acknowledge, oh yeah, the Torah declared by angels, yep.
And again, this isn't even...
a thing where, you know, there's been this new, new testament revelation, right?
Like if this is a gap that's being filled in, uh, St. Stephen or St. Paul had a vision
or something, or the Holy Spirit led them to this additional detail or that kind of thing.
Because we find this everywhere in Jewish sources outside of the New Testament also.
Yeah, so Josephus, you know, who is...
a writer that actually probably a lot of Protestants are aware of.
For whatever reason, he's kind of popular amongst a lot of Protestants.
As a, I think he's, because he's as a witness to a number of the things that are mentioned
in the New Testament, but he's not Christian.
He's a Jewish writer.
So in his antiquities of the Jews in chapter 50 or book 15, I think paragraph 163, he says,
and this is just, you know, he's just sort of telling the story, says, we ourselves have
I've learned from God the most
of our doctrines and the holiest part of our law by angels or delegates or one translation
I said I saw it said by angels or ambassadors, you know, right and and so Josephus who's a Pharisee
who becomes an apostate basically he yeah he collaborated with the Romans yeah well he eventually
declared that Rome was the Messiah so that's about his apostate as you could get for a for
for a century.
But he has this too, right? And so this is the antiquities of the Jews. What Flamie is just
if his is doing is he's laying out like the history of the Jewish people and their way of life
to his Roman patrons, right? That's who he's talking to, what he says we ourselves have learned
from God, right? The most excellent of our doctorate. So this is how he's explaining and expressing
the origin of the Torah.
to these Roman Gentiles who know nothing about Judaism.
Right.
So, this is just an accepted thing again.
So, the only place where we get this, as we mentioned, we don't get this laid out in Exodus.
Right.
Exodus doesn't lay out there being angels involved in the giving of the Torah.
Which is why when you watch, you know, the Ten Commandments with Charlton Heston, it's
him alone on the side of the mountain.
the voice of God, Moses, the letters
sewn up in the tablet, something that just fall out of the stone.
Yeah. Yeah. Which I love. I mean, I love that movie. But no, yeah, because it's not laid out in
Exodus that the angels are present. And yet you have these other references, not just in the
New Testament, but other literature from the period. Right. Right. And so the place where you find sort
of this in.
narrative form is in the book of Jubilies, which unless you're Ethiopian is not part of your old testament.
But which was a hugely influential work, it was the at Comoron where the Dead Sea Scrolls were found.
in terms of number of copies of different texts that we've discovered there. Number one is Genesis.
Number two is first Enoch. Number three is the book of Jubilee's. And when you
read Joseph Seifas' history, he incorporates a lot of details from the book of
Jubilee. So it's very clear it was an influence on him too. Yeah, and you know
for those of you who have not read Jubilee's, it's basically a retelling of
Genesis kind of up from a different angle. You know, it's essentially those same
events. Yeah. Yeah, a little expansionist, you know,
incorporating some other stories and details.
Yeah, so I mean, there's this reference in Jubilee's, I mean, this is right in the end of
the first chapter and the very, very beginning of the second one.
I'm just going to read it real quick, because I think it's important to just sort of hear
how this fits into this narrative says this.
And the Lord will appear to the eyes of all, and also know that I am the God of Israel,
the father of all the children of Jacob, and King on Mount Zion for
all eternity, and Zion and Jerusalem shall be holy.
And the angel of the presence who went before the camp of Israel took the tables of the
divisions of the years from the time of the creation, of the law and of the testimony
of the weeks of the Jubilee, according to the individual years, according to all the
number of the Jubilee's, according to the individual years, from the day of the new
creation when the heavens and the earth shall be renewed, and all their creation according
the powers of the
heaven, and according to all the creation of the earth, until the sanctuary of the Lord
shall be made in Jerusalem on Mount Zion, and all the luminaries be renewed for healing,
and for peace, and for blessing for all the elective Israel, and that thus it may be from
that day and unto all the days of the earth.
And the angel of the presence spake to Moses according to the word of the Lord saying,
right, the complete history of the creation, how in six days the Lord God finished all
all his works and all that he...
created and kept Sabbath on the seventh day and hallowed it for all ages and appointed
it as a sign for all his works.
And I'll just say this, it's interesting to me that at the end you get Moses being told
right down the creation, right?
Which, you know, this is probably a question that maybe some people have ever asked themselves
is, okay, so the tradition is that Moses writes Genesis, but who was there, you know, during
the six days of creation to run.
that down. And you know, and it's, this is Jubilee's explanation is that Moses gets told
this by this angel of the presence. And therefore then he's able to write it down because Moses
was not an eyewitness of the creation of Adam and Eve shocking. But he was not there. And Adam
did as far as we know Adam didn't write anything down. So yeah, and people forget, right, because
as big as big-
And it's not Saint Jerome's fault. He meant well, but because we've got that law, law word now, right?
We it's in referring to the Torah. We refer to the law of Moses all the time. And so we forget that Genesis is part of it.
Yeah, right, right, right. Right. Because we're thinking of law as in commandments. So we think, oh, that's like that Leviticus stuff.
Like Deuteronomy. That's that's the law.
But the whole thing is the Torah. The whole thing is the nomos. The whole thing is the lex.
Alright.
including Genesis. And so that's where it starts.
This also means, of course, that the angel of the presence was there when God created the world.
Which will be important next time.
Thank for shadowing.
Also, in the little more immediate for shadowing,
we have here, right? We saw those first couple quotes,
this idea that there were angels plural,
who sort of mediated the Torah.
but here we see that if
There are angels, but there's this one angel in particular called the angel of the presence.
And he's also the first time he's mentioned in the quote you just read, identified as the one who went before the camp of Israel.
And so that is less vague for shadowing for what we're going to talk about in the second half.
But this angel of the presence, this singular figure.
gets referred to in the third reference in the New Testament to the law being given by angels that we haven't mentioned yet.
Yeah, okay. So this is Galatians chapter three verses 19 and 20.
St. Paul says, why then the law? It was added because of transgressions until the offspring should come to whom the promise had been made
and it was put in place through angels by an intermediary.
Now an intermediary implies more than one
but God is one. And so St. Paul has just been talking about Abraham, right? And Abraham's seed,
right? So that's what he means by. So why the law? Why the Torah? Why is the Torah given? It's
given because of transgressions, right? To handle, to deal with sin, to deal with transgressions,
to manage sand and pollution and uncleanness.
Until the singular offspring...
of Abraham, the one who is the heir of the promises to Abraham until he comes the
laws there. And then the Torah is put in place through angels by an intermediary.
Now, if you stop at the end of verse 19, you might be tempted to think that
intermediary is Moses. Right? Moses is the mediator of this coming. But if
That's what St. Paul has in mind that verse 20 doesn't make a lot of sense.
Yeah, because he says now an intermediary implies more than one, but God is one.
So he's saying that the intermediary is God.
Right.
In addition to the angel's plural, there is this intermediary figure called in Jubilee's
the angel of the Presence, the singular intermediary figure.
but St. Paul wants to make clear.
Yes, we're referring to this figure as an intermediary between God and Moses, but we're
not implying that this intermediary is not God, or is it subway separate from the other
God of Israel?
Yeah, and if you, you know, if you listened to our episode about Abraham, you know that
the seed that the ultimate seed that St. Paul is referencing here, the seed of Abraham
Christ. That's that's that's who's being referenced here. Right. And so if we understand what St. Paul
is saying, he's saying that Christ gave the Torah to manage and deal with sins and transgressions
until he came. Right. Right. That's that's literally what St. Paul is saying. And so if anyone is
It's wonderful.
right? Well where does this come from? Right? I mean, if it's not in the text of Exodus,
right? And we're not going to say that Jubilee's is quote unquote inspired or something, right?
Right. Which is fine to do if you're Ethiopian, right? You can just say, well, there you go.
Isn't your Bible? Yes. Yes. So, but for the rest of us, you know, where does this idea come from?
Well, it does actually come from the text of
Exodus. If you read it very closely. Right. And you read it in a big chunk. Right? Because
this comes out of what seems to be an obvious contradiction in Exodus chapter 33. Yeah. Right.
And part of the issue with how we tend to read the Bible in general is that we only read it in
in little pieces.
We read it one story at a time.
which is good. It's good. You have to understand the parts in order to understand the whole. We have to read the pieces.
But we also need to sometimes read the whole, like read the whole thing so that we put the pieces together and see how the piece before relates to the piece after.
Because there's a lot of meaning that comes out of that. And this is an example of that in Exodus 33.
Yeah, yeah. So yeah, so in in excess 33
three, eleven in the first half of the verse, very famous passage. Thus the Lord used
to speak to Moses, face to face as a man speaks to his friend, right? So he's talking to
Moses, face to face.
Yeah. And the Lord there is Yahweh in the Hebrew.
Right. Yahweh spoke to Moses, face to face.
Right. Right. Which I always point this out when people sometimes say, well, no, you know,
You can't. No one saw.
in the Old Testament. I'm like, but it says that he spoke to him face to face right there.
Okay, so yeah, not too many verses down now. So again, this is Exodus chapter 33. This is verse 20 now
and this is God speaking, but he said, you cannot see my face for man shall not see me and live.
Two Moses. Two Moses, right? So like, yeah, so I mean, what's the explanation there?
literally it says the God you speak to Moses face to face
Jesus, man speaks to his friend and then later on God says,
you can't see my face because you're going to die, Moses.
Yeah.
Nine verses later.
And this is important that it's so close, right?
Because again, our 19th century German friends
will rear their hori heads.
And Von Rodd and all of them will show up and say,
well, that's because those are separate traditions
that contradict each other.
And they've all been edited together.
It's like, OK.
But these are...
This is nine versus a part. Yeah right. No one would have noticed that that there's a quote-unquote
contradiction written into it. One of these literary geniuses who crafted the Torah,
one of the great works of the ancient world even from a secular perspective, notice that they
contradicted themselves nine versus a part. Yeah, literally the most red text in human history.
Yeah, no, they didn't notice it.
Right, which is pretty absurd, right? So
Instead, what you see here is, and this is one of many passages that we're going to be talking about, not just tonight, but in this four-part series, where you see that there is that Yahweh, the God of Israel, is unseen and cannot be seen, and have someone live in this holiness he cannot be held by sinful humanity.
he can't be approached by sinful humanity, and yet at the same time.
people see Yahweh, talk to Yahweh, eat with Yahweh. Right. And so there is a Yahweh
who is unseen and there is a Yahweh who is seen. Right. And they're not to, as they
Paul makes clear in verse 20, they are not two different gods. They are both the one
Yahweh the God of Israel, because God is one.
And so this is where again, not to
but finally point out it, but this is where the whole concept of two hypostasis, right,
that later develops into three in the doctrine of the Trinity, right, this is ancient.
This isn't something they dreamed up in the fourth or fifth century as some kind of platonic
logic puzzle at the councils, so that somebody could claim authority because they didn't like an
air. I don't know what the conspiracy there is. Nor even something brand new in the New Testament,
any of the
there. Right. Right. So there is this idea. There is this figure. Right. There's the second
figure who is Yahweh, the God of Israel, but who is also a second person, a second figure.
And one of the ways that this figure is spoken of is the way we're speaking about
him tonight as the angel of the Lord. Right. Right. Okay. So we're going to go to break
very soon. But before we go to break, we had someone call in and leave us a message with
very specifically about what we're talking tonight.
And so we have a message from Kyle, who called in from Ireland.
Hello, fathers. My name is Kyle. I'm from Ireland.
I'm loving the show. Thank you very much for it.
My question is by the angel of the Lord.
I'll keep it short.
Are we to think of the angel of the Lord as the second person
of the Trinity, God, the Son, in a post-resurrectional body?
Thank you very much.
All right, so.
Did you have an answer for that, father?
Yes.
Dun dun dun dun.
OK, let's go to break.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Saint Ignatius, first century bishop of Antioch, called the God-bearer, is one of the earliest
witnesses to the truth of Christ and the nature of the Christian life.
Tradition tells us that as a small child, Ignatius was singled out by Jesus himself as
an example of the child-like faith all Christians must possess.
In bearing God, Father Andrew Damick recounts the life of this great pastor, martyr, and
and interprets for the
the modern reader, five major themes
in the past store letters he wrote.
Maridum, salvation and Christ,
the Bishop, the unity of the Church, and the Eucharist.
For Ignatius, Maridum is really the fullness
of Christ in my sense, which that can be challenging for us,
because, number one, he doesn't seem to have any
reticence at all about going to Maridum.
Like there's no sense of, well, this is what I have to do.
You know, I wish I didn't have to, but this is God's will for me.
He is going to it joyfully. Gladly.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.AncientFaith.com.
Again, that is store.AncientFaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
All right, welcome back everybody.
I always liked to end with a cliffhanger.
We haven't done that very in a while.
But I like the voice of Steve said, you're welcome to call in.
We want to talk to you about the angel of the Lord.
Okay, so I mean, before we begin, I just want to say it was very good of you to record
that book promo from within Leviathan.
Right.
That sort of sounds like...
Underwater somewhere.
I know. I know. You know, that's
That was from an interview that I did.
It's been a few years, and I think I did it over the phone before I had the magical tower
podcasting, in which I now reside.
Like a rotary phone?
Yeah, right.
I guess it's tap the thing and say, give me Greenville 6,000, that kind of thing.
Yeah, all our ancient Gen X listeners know what that is.
But we're the last generation to see them.
It's true.
So.
Right.
Kyle asks this question is the
the hands of the Lord, the second person of the Trinity
in a post-resurrectional body.
Yeah, I mean, and you said, yes, I stand by that.
Yeah, right.
I mean, I think it's worth noting that,
why is that true?
Well, it's because, right, it's because,
and just in brief, it's because...
What exactly does it mean to be in heaven?
What does it mean for Christ to be present?
When exactly is he?
And I went on purpose, right?
And we often describe him being incarnate without change.
That's the phrase used a lot in our liturgical services.
So, you know, that's a lot of what's going on there.
And in a future episode,
We are going to actually try to tackle some...
of these real mind-bending concepts that play into why this is the case because otherwise,
what are we talking about, right? Because it's clear that he's embodied in the Old Testament,
as we're going to see, right? But then to say that that's not his post-resurrectional,
quote unquote body, it suggests that he was incarnate as something else for a while.
Right. I mean, that's kind of the only place or that he made himself felt by, I don't
know, force fields or something. I don't know where else you can go with that.
Yeah. Well, yeah. And just to riff on it a little, yeah, tea break or something while I
riff, if you need to. All right. But yeah, unless, right, you're one of our Calvinist friends,
you don't think that Christ's body is off.
in some place somewhere as opposed to being other places.
Little bit of a cheap shop, but they know what I'm talking about.
They're used to it from you by.
Yeah. Yeah. Sorry, Calvinist.
Hit that bingo spot too.
So we're used to the realization that when we talk about heaven,
we're not talking about a place, a place up in the sky or a place somewhere
far off or replace anyway right that that
We're talking about an aspect of reality, a spiritual aspect of reality that isn't a different place, right?
Place, extension in distance and space is something that we experience in this created world, right?
And is experienced very differently by angelic beings and by God and by bat.
But we're not used to or as used to thinking about
time in the same terms. Right? That just as there's not like a direction you could point
like heavens that way, right? Or like GPS coordinates for heaven. That would be ridiculous.
Right? You all likewise get what time is it in heaven? Right? What what time zone is heaven in?
Right. What what would that even mean? Like the whole way we reckon time is based on the movements
of like the earth and the sun.
Right, and the moon and the planets.
So those time categories don't
don't fit either. They don't fit any better. Right. So there are, and we've used this terminology before, there are eternal realities.
Right. There are eternally true so that we can talk about Christ being slain before the foundation of the world. Right. And we can talk about
say Paul could say to the
Christians in and around Ephesus that they are already seated with Christ in the heavenly places
while they're suffering on this earth. So there's this there's this eternal reality
and that eternal reality enters into our human experience at certain points
within our human experience. Time and space are descriptors and categories that frame
our human experience and allow us to order it.
Right. So when when Hebrews says that Christ is the same yesterday and today and forever, right?
It means the yesterday part. Yes. Right. Not just Christ is never going to change, right?
But he never did. Right? That's why the fathers and our himnography are so clear. Christ is incarnate
without change or alteration. Yeah. And it kind of underlines also the notion that he is the first
and sport overall creation as well.
not just in that place of being first born, you know, the one who distributes the inheritance,
but that he's also the first born, you know? Right. Yeah. Yeah. So, yeah. And so that's hard for
us to wrap our brains around because they're human brains. And we experience everything in terms
of time and space and other categories of phenomenology.
have to accept that, that's for us humans. That's not for angels, that's not for bats,
that it's definitely not for God. And Christ is God.
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So in the second part of the show, we're going to be talking some more
about this figure, the angel of the Lord, but now from a kind of a different angle.
And particularly this angle is the
the angle of we're not referring to St. Michael.
That's what this is about.
So just going to keep that as a framing device in your head
that it's not St. Michael.
I mean, we have St. Michael, we're big fans of St. Michael.
We really need him, but this is not St. Michael.
Right. And this is, there are a number of appearances.
We're going to go through pretty much all of them.
Appearances of the angel of the Lord in the Old Testament.
right, but in this
second half there is one you can't even really call it an appearance because it's an arc
it's a it's a narrative arc covering you know close to a century of time right within
the scriptures in which the angel of the Lord is directly involved and so this second half is
is going to be talking about that.
of Ark. Yeah. Right. That involves a whole bunch of different humans, but also the Angel of the Lord.
And so that kind of Ark begins with the Angel of Yahweh, not so much appearing, but being designated
it and described by God in Exodus chapter 23.
Yeah.
So in Exodus 23 verses 20.
versus 20
21, God says this, behold, I send an angel before you to guard you on the way as to bring you to the
place that I've prepared. Pay careful attention to him and obey his voice. Do not rebel against him,
for he will not pardon your transgression. For my name is in him. That's kind of a weird thing to
to say they're at the end. Yeah, right. And remember.
This is the payoff of that, that mention in Jubilee's that the angel of the presence who gave the Torah is the angel who led
Right the camp of the Israelites, right the one who went before them. So this is the same figure. Right. So this is this is who Jubilee's was talking about Jubilee's is saying this
Angel figure is the one who also gave the Torah
So yeah, so a couple pieces as you mentioned that my name is in him, right?
right. Um.
There's a tendency by some folks, including some folks online, whenever they see name with
a capital N, the name of the Lord, or even in the Hebrew, the name of Yahweh, they interpret
that as meaning like Yahweh.
That means the four consonants, the tetragramaton.
That's what that means.
The word itself, in other words.
Right, the actual four.
right? And there are a number of places, this being one of them, where that
understanding just doesn't make any sense. Right? So if I will put my name in
him means the four consonants, like what does that mean? Like inside of him is
going to be written somewhere, the name Yahweh, right? The four consonants are
going to be written on an internal, well, I guess angels don't have internal
organs, but maybe they do.
I don't know.
Like, that doesn't make any sense, right?
And there are other places, you know,
where it talks about, you know,
the name of Yahweh protecting people, right?
And that doesn't mean like they're gonna write it
in the sand as a magical charm
and no one will be able to cross
the consonants written in the sand or something
to protect them, right?
This isn't some kind of ritual magic thing, right?
It's talking about something else, right?
Name with the capital N in there
is referring to something else.
And
and specifically it's referring, right, name someone's name in the ancient world also means
their identity. And we still use it that way in English, right? This person made a name for
himself where he has a good name in the community, right? Meaning like his reputation, his identity,
how he's seen, right? And there are lots of places where that's obviously what's going on with
with that term. So people will appeal to God in the Old Testament.
When they know they've done wrong, they know they've been wicked and they're seeking God's forgiveness
and they'll say, well, pardon us, like the people of Israel, pardon us, do not be rattle with us for your namesake.
So that the nations won't speak badly about you, that you brought us out of Egypt and they killed us all in the desert.
Right. So show mercy on us for the sake of your reputation of nothing else. We don't deserve it, but
Don't let your name be drugged through the mud, but that idea of identity, right, is important
and so when when you know the god of Israel says he's going to put his name the place where I will put my name
referring to the tabernacle and then the temple, right?
In Jerusalem, that's the place where he is going to be, right? That's that's what he means. So when he says
right, that his name is going to be in this angel.
this being who's going to lead them, right? That means that his identity, who he is, is going to be in him.
Yeah. And that then we see elements of this in the New Testament with reference to Christ in a couple of different ways.
So in one sense what we talk about the name being placed in the tabernacle and in the first temple
There's this the we're bringing it back the theophonic glory cloud
Right. As I'm inclined to do, it appears, right. And that's a manifestation of the Holy Spirit,
right, just as the pillar of fire, the pillar of smoke, right, is this manifestation of the Holy
Spirit, right, the presence of God. And so we see, for example, in John 1 verse 33,
Right?
the way in which St John the forerunner knew who Jesus was, knew who the Messiah was,
according to him. Yeah, so this was St John. The forerunner says, I myself did not know him,
but he who sent me to baptize with water said to me, he on whom you see the spirit descend
and remain, this is he who baptizes with the Holy Spirit. Right. And so the symbol that's given
to Moses.
to say, this is how you will know my angel, right? Who this is, who's going to lead you, right?
Through the wilderness into the land, is the same sign that's given to St. John the Forerunner to identify Jesus.
In that sense, right?
Yeah, the name, the Spirit.
Right. And we also see in terms of the Holy Spirit dwelling within Christ,
not only the references to himself as a as a temple, but
But this is what's going on.
You note in that last part of the verses we read from Exodus,
do not rebel against him, for he will not pardon your transgression for my name is in him.
Right?
That this is going to be serious now if you rebel against it because he's going to be with you,
you're going to be more accountable.
And there will not be forgiveness if you rebel against him.
This makes sense of one of the passages that gets people really worried
and Mark that's also paralleled in math.
you. Yeah, this reference to, you know, if you blaspheme against the Holy Spirit, then it's not
going to be forgiven you. And of course, you know, I remember when I was young, you know, growing up in
low church Protestant circles, the people trying to figure out what exactly is the sin that is the
blaspheme against the Holy Spirit, you know, because if you commit that one, well, there's no forgiveness.
And you know, you're on your way to hell as a result, kind of missing the point here.
which is that it's an emphasis on the divinity of Christ and on the Holy Spirit as well.
Right. That because Christ was in their midst, literally, right?
Directly, they're speaking to them, that their rebellion against him, they're accusing him of being
demon-possessed in both of those cases. Right? That rebellion is not going to find forgiveness.
there are more accountable now.
Right, then they would be if he was not there.
Right.
Which he says repeatedly in St. John's Gospel,
if I had not come to you, you would not have sinned.
Right. Right.
Yeah.
But so we mentioned that there are a couple ways in which that the name being present,
the identity of God being present in Christ is expressed.
The other way is there are a series of references in St. John's Gospel
and say John's Gospel 14 verse 11.
in 20 and 17 verse 23 and a few others that talk about the Father being in Christ.
That the Father's in him, right? This is the same idea, right, that that is being expressed
in the Old Testament. So in the Old Testament here to be clear, right? This figure is being
described, the angel of the Lord is being described in the same terms that Christ is described
in the gospels.
Right. And sort of
in hearing, so to speak, of the persons of the Trinity with one another.
Right. And he is now going to be leading Israel out of Egypt and into the wilderness.
And we actually see him exercising this role, and if you place it again, it's easy to kind of skim over these and not notice.
And there's one of these in Exodus chapter
14 versus 19 and 20 and this is where Pharaoh's armies have sort of
started now chasing after Israel after Israel has left Egypt and Israel has come to the Red Sea
and now they're kind of between Iraq and a hard place they've got the Red Sea on one side
and they've got you know and we've talked about how that death is involved with that so they've got
the Red Sea they've got death on one side and they've got Pharaoh and his armies on the other side
and they're sort of squished in between.
And Yahweh talks to Moses and says that he hears his voice and says, you know, that he's going to protect him and to gather the people next to the sea.
And then in verse 19, this happens.
Which again is not in the Charles and Heston film.
Yeah.
Which it should be.
I mean, come on.
Okay.
So X is 14.
Verse 19.
and twenty, then the angel of God who is going before the host of his
moved and went behind them and the pillar of cloud moved from before them and stood
behind them coming between the host of Egypt and the host of Israel and there was
the cloud and the darkness and it lit up the night without one coming near the
other all night and so you know there's this he becomes the rear guard so to
speak right right so that Israel can escape and right and here next to the
water.
We see the voice of the father, right?
We see the angel of Yahweh, right?
Christ and we see the Holy Spirit in the pillar of cloud.
All manifest here by the water.
Hint, hint for January.
There you go.
But also, right?
It's this, all three are as one,
acting to protect Israel, right?
to protect.
the people of God.
And there is a place in the New Testament
that very directly interprets this angel as being Christ.
Yeah, which is kind of hidden again
in translation issues and what we'll explain
exactly why this is the case.
Okay, so this is Jude verse 5.
There's only one chapter.
So it's Jude 5.
Now I want to remind you.
Although you once fully knew it, that Jesus, who saved a people out of the land of Egypt,
afterward destroyed those who did not believe.
Now, the reason why this is a little hidden is because a lot of translations of the Bible
up to, what, just maybe a few decades ago, said, the Lord who saved a people out of the
land of Egypt.
But here it's Jesus.
Okay, so what's going on? Why should it be? Why should the translation be Jesus?
I mean, it's clearly those are two different words even in Greek.
Right.
We, well, yeah, and the, of course, the Lord could there mean Jesus.
I mean, it's not, it's not wrong.
Yeah.
It's just not as specific as a specific.
Right.
And so basically what happened is we found a bunch of much older manuscripts.
Well, not a bunch.
We found some older, much older manuscripts of Saint Jude's epistle.
And these older
We've got the ones we found all have Jesus there.
All have the name Jesus there.
Yeah, so you got Jesus standing there on the shore of the Red Sea.
Right.
And it's now pretty clear.
And it's so clear now that there's really nobody out there who's arguing for Lord,
except for maybe some King James only books.
I should say nobody.
There's somebody out there arguing everything on the internet.
But it's true.
In terms of New Testament scholars, right?
There's nobody really
arguing that that's not Jesus there. And it's fun to watch people who don't like
talking about Christ in the Old Testament, bend over backwards into bizarre yoga
positions, to try to explain what this is talking about, including, I won't name
the person, they named themselves frequently enough, but trying to argue that it's
talking about Joshua like Old Testament Joshua.
Right.
who I guess in his mind saved people out of Egypt and then killed them all in the desert.
After we destroyed those who did not believe it, it says they're in Jude 5.
Right. Yeah, because Joshua and Jesus are the same name.
Is the claim? I mean, it is. They are. They are the same name. But they're trying to claim it was
Joshua, you know, who was the servant of Moses and becomes a successor, who did this. But that doesn't
make any sense.
in the whole verse.
Right, right.
And so this is very clearly talking about this figure.
Right.
Who led the people out of Egypt and then who,
as we're going to see some examples of in the third half,
destroying a lot of the, those who did not believe.
So a big part of this, you know, moving on in Exodus 23,
after what we read already about the angel, right?
Uh.
Yahweh, the God of Israel, in talking to Moses goes on to outline sort of what this is going
to be about.
So he read up to the warning where if you rebel against him, it's not going to be forgiven.
But then in verse 22, he makes a promise in the other direction.
Yeah.
And he says this, but if you carefully obey his voice and do all that I say, then I will
be an enemy to your enemies and an adversary to your adversaries.
which is interesting, you notice the shift there.
If you carefully obey his voice and do all that I say,
then I will be an enemy to your enemies and adversaries.
Again, this close association between the father who's speaking
and the angel of the Lord that's being sent out in front of the armies.
Right. And so they're completely on the same page.
Right. And this is, again, the way this is going to get put
this is gonna get put by the fathers.
is one nature, one will, one energy, right?
But they're saying and doing the same thing.
As Christ is going to say over and over again,
it's Saint John's gospel, right?
He does what the Father does.
He says what the Father says, right?
But the call here then, the promise is that if the people
of Israel align themselves then
with that will and that energy, right?
with what God is doing in the world.
and with good desires.
If they align themselves and participate in it,
then they will be on the same side as Yahweh,
the God of Israel.
He will be their God.
He will be the enemy of their enemies.
The adversary there ever says,
he will lead them into battle.
They won't be on their own.
They won't be subject to superior numbers.
But God in the person of the angel of Yahweh
will lead them.
and this isn't just sort of a...
hypothetical thing about adversaries because in the next couple verses and
Exodus 23 those adversaries get listed. Yeah, right. Like these are actual battles
that are about to happen. So verse 23, when my angel goes before you and brings you
to the emerites and the hitites and the parasites and the canonites, the
hyvites and the jabby sites and I blot them out, you shall not bow down to their
gods nor serve them nor do as they do, but you shall utterly overthrow them and
and break their pillar.
in pieces. No neutral grout. Right. Yeah. Yeah. Don't buy down to their gods. Hello. And yes, folks,
here's the giants. Right. Yes. Emeralds. So, yeah. Gigantomachy here is the purpose of the Exodus.
Yep. It's not just I'm going to free some slaves and give them a nice place to live. Right. Yeah,
they're being sent out. They're sent on a mission. Right?
remove these giant clans, right? And notice here what? How blotting them out is
defined? Blotting them out is not defined as exterminating their DNA. Right. Yeah,
it's about yeah, it's about overthrowing the their worship breaking breaking their
pillars and pieces. This is about destroying temples and stuff. You know, it's
about getting rid of the gods and the paganism, you know, the actual practices of
worshipping these gods. Right, the religious rituals
that constitute these people groups.
Yeah, and of course if you end the rituals
then the people groups don't exist anymore.
Right, they dissolve into other people groups.
Preferably, Israel.
Right, ideally.
Yeah, so right, so this is sort of the beginning
of that arc that we mentioned at the beginning of this half.
Right, that now we have this figure who's going to lead them.
So now we're going to check in in the book of Joshua.
All right.
sort of in media race, right?
For the beginning of, not really the beginning,
but early on in those battles that we just heard about,
specifically in Joshua chapter five.
And the first part of Joshua chapter five
before we get to the angel of the Lord,
is this, we just crossed the Jordan River, right?
The Jordan is parted in front of the people
But they were...
brought the Ark of the Covenant to it, they've passed through the Jordan on dry ground,
and they're now going to begin the conquest proper.
They're now going to face off with these giant clans.
And so what does Joshua do with the people?
Right?
Well, what was Moses told to do?
If you want the angel of Yahweh to lead you into battle and defeat your enemies, then
You need to align yourself with Yahweh, the God of Israel.
And so he does that by first circumsizing, right?
The people and then they celebrate the Passover.
Yeah, and you might wonder like, wait,
I thought that these people were circumcised, right?
Explains in Joshua 5.4 and this is, I'm quoting,
and this is the reason why Joshua circumcised them.
All the males of the people who came out of Egypt,
all the men of war had died in the wilderness
on the way after they had come out of Egypt.
What that means is that the ones who had been circumcised, they didn't actually circumcise
their own sons, meaning they became unfaithful to Yahweh.
They were not doing the thing that you were supposed to do for people to be in the covenant.
And so this is a renewal of that covenant, which includes both the entrance into the covenant
via circumcision and then the fulfillment of what it means to really be Israel, which is
you celebrate the Passover, right? Because that's what made them
That's what constitute them as a nation in the first place.
And then it gets repeated over and over again,
and perpetuated.
Just as the giant clans are constituted
by their demonic rituals, right?
It's circumcision and the eating of the Passover
that constitute Israel generationally.
Right, right.
And then that we've talked about before,
and we'll have sure we'll talk about again,
how that goes into baptism in the Eucharist, right?
Right, exactly.
And receiving the Eucharist in the church
is what constitutes the Church.
as a people, as a nation.
Right, so, so, yeah, so, you know, getting the people ready now, renewing their faithfulness
to God, you know, bringing them back into alignment with Him, and then this happens.
So verse 13, yeah, go ahead.
Yeah, they, they, they align themselves with God, right, and then who shows up, right?
Verses of His promise.
Exactly, yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, verse 13.
Joshua 5, when Joshua was by Jericho, I'm going to read a few verses here, when Joshua was by Jericho
he lifted up his eyes and looked and behold a man was standing before him with his drawn sword in his hand
and Joshua went to him and said to him, are you for us or for our adversaries? And he said no.
But I am the commander of the army of the Lord. Now I have come and Joshua fell in his face to
the earth and work.
and said to him, what does my Lord say to his servant?
And the command of the Lord's army said to Joshua,
take off your sandals from your feet
for the place where you are standing as holy
and Joshua did so. Lots of fun stuff there.
Right, right. And so we have to take note here
with this passage, right, that there is
within the Derser the Orthodox Church,
there is a minority position.
position as you alluded to in your intro to this half.
There's a minority position that identifies this figure, the commander of Yahweh's hosts, as Saint Michael.
Right.
There's at least one Sinekzarian that does that.
I think there's a him.
I know there are a couple of church fathers to do.
Now this is a minority position, but we're trying to be good corporate citizens here.
Marl, Marl...
good behavior. When we're talking about the tradition of the church and we're talking
about the writings of the church fathers and we're talking about our liturgical tradition,
right? That doesn't represent a range of options for us, right? That's not how you do it,
right? That's not how any of this works, right? The way this works is we want to orient ourselves
within the tradition is on.
whole. And so that means if we're going to say that some part of the tradition that conflicts
with other parts of the tradition got it wrong, we have to then explain how. We have to give an
explanation, right, of, well, where does this minority report come from? Or at least, why is that
minority report not correct? Okay. And so that's, that's what we're now going to endeavor to do.
is try to show from this text why we would agree with the majority.
in the Orthodox tradition that identifies this with the angel of the Lord and with Christ,
starting all the way back with St. Justin, martyr, St. Justin, the philosopher in the second century.
Right. In terms of church tradition, and before that in Jewish writings.
So there are three details here in those three verses you read that we're going to point at.
The first one is that
Joshua sees him with this drawn sword next to Jericho, which they're about to
attack spoilers. You may have heard that story. Yes, I sang a song about this when
I was quite young, along with many other children in Sunday school. Little
known liturgical fact that I'm sure all of the liturgic scholars listening will
vouch for. The reason we go around things three times instead of seven is that
we did seven they would collapse.
So who would collapse the walls are us.
Maybe both.
Yeah.
I heard all those dose.
So.
Yeah.
But so this this drawn sword.
Seeing this figure with a drawn sword.
This is imagery that's used elsewhere in the Old Testament.
Both before and after.
And so that the instance before or instances before
from the connected.
This is in Numbers chapter 22, which is the story of Baelum and his donkey, which we're
going to talk about more in the third half teaser.
But there the angel of Yahweh appears and he has this drawn sword.
Right.
And that's one of his identifiers.
Later one is in First Chronicles 21, 16.
We're also going to talk about that one in the third half in more detail.
But there also the angel the Lord appears with a drawn sort.
to David. Right. And then the third time is where this drawn sword imagery appears is in
Ezekiel 21, really the whole that's all through the chapter, but verses four and five in verse
28, and there it's Yahweh himself who has drawn his sword and has a drawn sword.
Yeah, and I mean you can see like there's an icon of Christ with a sword which is, I mean it's this
right? You know it's funny I sometimes see that.
icon used in context where I think people intend it to be like, you know, the sort of, I
don't know, you know, like here, here's, look, here's Jesus with a sword, you know, back
away, heretics. You know, that's, but that's not, that's not what's going on in these passages
in the scripture judgment on Israel. Yeah, right. Right. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. But so that's,
So that's...
point one in our case, right, that that imagery is imagery that's used for the angel of the
of Yahweh and for Yahweh himself elsewhere in the Old Testament where it's used, right?
Right.
And so that's an identifier of this figure.
Second point is that Joshua falls on his face on the earth and worshiped him.
Yep, right.
And he doesn't say, get up, man.
I'm not, you know, I'm just like you.
Yes.
You see angels do.
Right. They've been frequent.
right in the scriptures. And so if someone is going to say that this is Saint Michael,
they have to then explain why Saint Michael is here allowed to receive worship.
Right. Why he doesn't say anything. And then the third point is the actual response
when he worships him, rather than saying don't is,
Commander Lord's army says, take off your sandals from your feet for the place where you are
standing as holy, which is an exact
quote of what the angel of the Lord, the angel of Yahweh says in Exodus, which will also be talking about in
Act 3. Right? So each of those three verses in various fairly clear ways identifies this as the angel of the Lord over against
Saint Michael. And so that's why we take that position. Yeah, within the tradition and think you should do
But we're not going to come to your house and beat you on the head if you don't. I might
Father's deep in my foot. No, no. Yeah. No, I'm I'm on probation. So I couldn't
get any way your under orders. Yeah. Yeah. So that's that's then the sort of
midpoint of this arc. Right. So the angel, the Lord, the angel of Yahweh
leads them through the wilderness leads them into battle in the conquest. So all
all that stuff that happens in Joshua that you can read about him.
my recent book. All of that stuff is being led by the angel of the Lord. Keep that in mind.
It's being led by Christ. All right. All that gigantomaki. And then we get to the end of that
arc in the second chapter of the book of Judges. Yeah. So this is Judges chapter two versus one
through five. Now the angel the Lord went up from
Gilgal to bokeh him.
And he said,
I brought you up from Egypt and brought you into the land
that I swore to give your fathers.
I said,
I will never break my covenant with you
and you shall make no covenant with the inhabitants
of this land.
You shall break down their altars,
but you have not obeyed my voice.
What is this you have done?
So now I say,
I will not drive them out before you,
but they shall become thorns in your sides
and their gods shall be a snare to you.
As soon as the angel of the Lord spoke.
these words to all the people of Israel, the people lifted up their voices and wept. And
they called the name of that place, Bokim, and they sacrificed there to the Lord.
Yeah. Bokim means weeping. Yeah, okay. That's why they called it that.
Yeah. Yeah. And I mean, this is, you know, so he's been, he's been with them all this time.
They did the thing he told them not to do. And so he leaves and says, your guys are now going to
you're going to, you know, your enemies are going to overtake you and their gods are going to be a snare for you.
Yeah. And this is the exact wording from back in Exodus 22.
Yeah.
The thing that told you not to do, you just destroy, you said destroy all of those idols,
because if you don't, they'll be a snare to you.
Right. And so here, you went and worshiped them. Right. And now they're going to be a snare to you.
Right. So it's, it's exactly, you know, concluding, concluding that arc.
that arc.
But we see here the angel of the Lord travels from one place to another.
Right? Right? It's not just he appeared at this one place. He travels from one place to another,
meaning he has continued to be with them this entire time.
He has continued to be with the people who are this entire time,
until now when he leaves. Notice also that when the angel of the Lord speaks here, where the angel
So we always speak here, he speaks in the first person.
He says, I brought you up from Egypt and brought you into the land that I swore to give to your fathers.
I said, I will never break my covenant with you.
So now I say, I will not drive them out before you.
So this is all first person.
Your average angel, even archangels, St. Michael, don't speak in the first person this way.
as St. Michael didn't...
make any oaths to Abraham or any promises. Right. That's he didn't make the covenant. It's not his covenant. Right.
So the angel of Yahweh is speaking in the first person as Yahweh here,
saying he did things not just in terms of, you know, Yahweh said he bring the matter of Egypt. Now
the angel of Yahweh is saying he brought them out of Egypt. But also he's saying he did things that
Yahweh did it back in
Genesis with Abraham in terms of the promises and the covenants.
And so there are plenty of places where he delisted, there are plenty of places he will
test them at where of course, you know, himself says he brought them and was going to bring them,
he did bring them out of Egypt. It's beginning of the 10 commandments. Right. Yeah. I mean,
it's one of the classic things like, hey, everybody, remember me? I'm the one who brought you out of
of Egypt. You know, like this is God talking about himself over and over again. He's
He says he defines himself this way.
Right, but here it's the angel of Yahweh
who's saying that in the first person.
Yeah.
And so, yeah, because of the idolatry, he now departs.
I wanna add one note here, right?
Cause we talked about this in terms of the dynamic
between the flood and the tower of Bable, right?
That God didn't want to destroy humanity again
and so he had to leave.
Right?
So even in the angel of the Lord of the Living,
remember that lack of forgiveness, right?
Those dumb...
consequences for rebelling against him while he was there. Right? So his departure is itself a mercy
for this rebellious people. Yep, because you don't want to be doing that stuff right in his face.
Right. It's better if he's not there, if that's what they're going to do.
And, and, and, you know, and honestly, it's, this is a sort of handing them over to Satan,
right? They're being ensnared by these false gods and they're going to suffer for that,
the point being to
I hope bring them to repentance.
Right.
Yep, you have it.
All right, well, that is our second half
and we'll be right back with a third half
right after this break.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Hi, this is John Maddox. You know when you support ancient faith radio, you're not only
helping to make this ministry possible for you, but also for people like Bryce in Australia.
I'd firstly just like to say that I love your show and what you do. It means a lot to
all of us listening. I'm down in Australia and over here, orthodoxy is basically unheard
I'm not orthodox, I was raised into an evangelical...
Protestant family. However, from a gradual exposure and desire to learn more about orthodoxy,
I've come to agree and see truth in pretty much everything that church teaches.
The nearest English-speaking orthodox church is several hours away,
and I feel all alone in my pursuit of the faith here. Currently, my only exposure to orthodoxy
is through ancient faith radio and my friend. How should I introduce the idea that I may be
inquiring into orthodoxy to my parents? Thanks again, for us. Would you consider a donation to AFR
right now you can do so on our app or go to our website at ancientfaith.com
slash support ancient faith radio here for you and for people all over the
world
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back everybody.
This is the third half of the show.
Before we get into third half, I actually wanted to just pass on a question that we got
on Facebook.
which I replied to the the asker, but I think it just might be useful for people to hear.
It's not totally on topic, but it's kind of generally about the show. So Bradley asks this,
he says, I have a sincere and curious question. What is your guys all time favorite Bible translation
in English as in the most accurate for linguistics and hermitted studies and for following along
with this podcast. And what I told him is that we often quote from the ESV but
but probably maybe just as often
or maybe not quite as often
we're reading your translation father.
I don't know.
Which is not commercially available,
therefore does not help him.
Yeah, right, exactly.
Yeah, he lists off in his question.
He says, he says,
I own the OSB, KJV, Dewey Reams, Knox, NKJV,
RSVCE, NRSVCE, NAB, NABRE, NIVESV,
NLT Jerusalem, Bible and Revised Jerusalem.
I don't see the width.
Cliff Bible in there, Bradley.
The B-I-B-L-E, that's the book for me.
Yeah. So you got most of them.
Yeah.
Yeah. So, um, yeah, it kind of depends on what you're doing.
You said you want to most accurate.
Yeah. I mean, if you're going to do, I know you've heard me do this before.
If you want to do more deep digging in Bible stuff
and you're not able to do the language,
the original languages, which is most people, right?
Sure, one, two more studying, and that's fine.
That's okay.
I usually recommend that people get an NET full notes version.
Yeah, which if you haven't seen,
and by the way, you can check this out,
if yourself online, right,
if you just simply go to netbible.org,
you can see with the content
is. And what that is is it's you know like for instance if you if you
terms with John chapter one you see this tiny little text in the middle of
the top and that's the biblical text and then reams of translators and
notes underneath it which is which is what I mean that's what this book is
it's it's piles and piles now that doesn't that's not to say that you know we
would necessarily agree with everything that's in the notes but you can see
what they're doing right right that's what's a
And that's why it's important that you get the full notes edition. I don't think the translation by itself
is a huge improvement over like the ESV or
the RSV or a number of other English translations. But those notes if you get the full notes
kind of let you behind the curtain as an English reader
into what they're doing. So they can see what they're doing and decide whether you agree with them or not.
Which you don't get with most translations.
Yeah. They kind of show their work. And because the scholars who did that and put it together made it public domain, you can get print copies relatively cheaply.
Yeah, I have a decent hardcover one that I got for like $35 or something like that, I think.
Yeah. But remember, make sure you get the one that says Knight Bible with full notes.
Yeah, full notes edition. Yeah, full notes.
So that's really good.
In terms of if you're just gonna read a translation and you...
don't want to dig into notes like that. The thing that's probably the closest is still
the old NASB, not the newer edition they did recently. It's okay, the newer edition. But
yeah, the sort of the class, NASB classic is fairly, when the literal,
fairly to the point that some of the sentences are unwieldy and hard to read.
But, you know,
know. So that's that's something the the ESV which I'll let you in on the big secret
because I like doing this. The ESV is the RSV. Yeah, it's just updated a little bit as
yet. 96% of the text is identical. Yeah, between the RSV and the ESV. The other 4% are
updates like that thing in Jude 5 that we talked about. Yeah, we were reading from the
Yes, we just that that
based on new textual finds, right, is that where and Dead Sea Scrolls where they updated
some things in the Old Testament, and those Dead Sea Scrolls updates in the Old Testament
mostly bring it closer to the Greek.
So from an Orthodox perspective, great, right?
Yeah.
And the RSV is already, RSV is the first major English translation of the Bible that had
Orthodox input into the translation.
Hmm.
A lot of folks don't know that.
So yeah.
the ESV because the ESV was the basis for the Reformation Study Bible. It's gotten this
rep as being like the Calvinist translation, but it's really not. It's just the RSV.
That's just propaganda. So yeah, hopefully that's...
Yeah, I mean, my approach as so many people is... I just own a lot of Bibles.
And because I mean we live in an era in which owning a lot of Bibles or even having a bunch of them
on your phone.
is not hard and not really that expensive.
So I think it's just worth it.
If you, especially if you're really trying to get underneath
the language a little bit to do that.
But there's no silver bullet, unfortunately.
That's OK.
Yeah, there is no perfect.
Even if I did from scratch do my own translation
of the whole Bible, there'll be plenty of people
who would disagree with it.
They'd probably be right about some of the disagreements.
Yeah.
Right, so...
I did the old NT right line that when he started teaching he used to tell everybody at the
beginning of his classes 10% of what I'm about to teach you is wrong.
I don't know what 10% or I would fix it, right?
Just keep that in mind.
And he said after you've been teaching for 20 years he started saying 20% of what I'm about
to teach you is wrong.
So say it applies to me, right?
Like, you know, I get things wrong.
That's not news to most listeners.
I don't think.
But right. So there will never be sort of a perfect Bible translation because no individual is
perfect to do it. And no committee has ever done anything well in the history of mankind.
So all right. So the third hopefully that helps Bradley and probably helps a lot of other people too.
I hope least somewhat. So in the third half, we're going to simply talk about a bunch of other
times a tangel of the Lord shows up, but I think it's important to just go over these.
just so we get some, again, the whole point is to get a broad picture of who the angel of the Lord is
as depicted in Holy Scriptures. And this, the first, first of four parts of Old Testament Christology episodes we're going to have.
So, all right, so the first one we're going to look at is from Exodus chapter three.
And this is a big one. I mean, this is a really, really famous one. This is where Moses sees the burning bush.
So, Exodus 3 verses 1 through 6, now Moses was keeping the flock of his father-in-law,
Jethro, the priest of Midian, and he led his flock to the west side of the wilderness and
came to horib the mountain of God.
And the angel of the Lord appeared to him in a flame of fire out of the midst of a bush.
He looked and behold the bush was burning, yet it was not consumed.
As Moses said, I will turn aside to see this great.
why the bush is not burned. When the Lord saw that, he turned aside to see God called to him
out of the bush. Moses, Moses, and he said, here I am. Then he said, do not come near, take your
sandals off your feet for the place on which you are standing is holy ground. And he said, I am the
God of your father, the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob. And Moses hid his
space for he was afraid to look.
God. The first thing I want to mention here, just in terms of setting, because I think this is important.
If you listen closely, it notices that Moses went to
horib the mountain of God and saw the burning bush. And you know, you might think
yourself, wait a minute, I thought the burning bush was at Sinai. And you would be correct,
because if you listen to our
say good geography episodes you know
that the mount
of God is wherever God has made that mountain be being the mountain of God. So that means that the
burning bush which Moses saw at Horib is being the burning bush that is on Mount Sinai right now
that's in the monastery there on Sinai. So it is the same, it is being the burning bush.
But I just wanted to point that out because a lot of people, oh yeah, the burning bush is a
Yes, it is.
but it also was at Horib at this point in Exodus 3.
Yeah. Yeah. And so, yeah, for our purposes here in terms of the angel of Yahweh,
in verse 2 there of Exodus 3, it's the angel of the Lord who appears to him in a flame, a fire out
of the midst of the bush, and then God calls to him out of the bush. Yeah, verse 4, right?
right? Right. And then he says that he's the God of Abraham and Isaac and
Jacob. Right? Yeah. Very clearly the angel of the Lord is God. Right. And there is a reason
it is not pure metaphor. It is not allegory that when you see an icon of Moses at the burning
bush, you see Christ in the bush. Yeah. Right. You see Christ and thrown in the lap of his mother,
that they are tocos surrounded by the
the Shrewpic throne, right? Because Christ there in Moses' day is enthroned both on his
human mother and on the throne of God, because he is God and man. But yeah, that's not a
weird anachronism. That's not symbolic and a vague fru-frusense. That is who called to
from
the bush. Right. Yeah. Like if this were a map, this would be the you are here. You know,
it is all those things at the same time. Yeah. And as we alluded to in the second half,
that what is said here about taking off the sandals for the place you're standing on his holy ground
is the exact same thing the commander of the Lord's Host says to Joshua. Yep.
with Joshua Paul's down in worship.
Beating.
the same person talking. Right. It has the same expectations of how to respond to him.
Right. And what makes it holy ground is not that this is some kind of sacred locale.
Right. Like Moses stumbled upon some ancient shrine. Yeah. It's because God is there on
that ground. It has become holy ground. It's because his presence is there. You're now
in his presence. That means the same thing is true with the commander.
of Yahweh's hosts with Joshua when he says that, is because God is standing there in front
of him that it's holy. And Moses is here afraid to see God even though he hid his face.
So that's one. Here's one we're getting into the book of judges here. People love it when
to talk about the book of churches.
thrilled every time I bring it up. This is actually in judges six and so this is, there's this cycle
that repeats all through the book of judges that we saw that cycle starts when the angel of Yahweh
departs, right? He leaves and then because of that, because God is not there fighting their battles
for them, these foreign oppressors come in, right? They sin, the foreign oppressors come in and conquer
for them.
being conquered is bad. And so they cry out to God for deliverance and at least make a show of repentance. God raises up a judge to deliver them.
They're delivered. They go back to sinning, right? This sort of endless cycle.
Yeah, and it gets worse as you do. It gets worse and worse. It's a downward spiral.
Yeah, so, and this part of the cycle.
here in Judges 6, it's the Midianites, right? Who are Edamites and Ishmaelites, right? These are
the people who actually Moses' wife was, right? But they've come and they're now a pressing part of
part of Israel, and the people right before the part we're going to talk about in Judges 6 versus 7
through ten, they cry out for deliverance. God sends a human profit to them.
who says Yahweh, the God of Israel has heard you,
he is going to deliver you.
And then in verse 11 he sends the angel of Yahweh
then appears to Gideon.
Yeah.
For Gideon to be the guy who's going to do this,
even though Gideon himself is not so keen on it,
necessarily.
And so what we read there in judges six
versus 11 through 24 sort of briefly is.
the angel of the Lord appears,
and the angel of Yahweh appears
and Gideon speaks to him.
And then verse 14 says,
then Yahweh turned to him and said,
Yeah, which interestingly in the Greek,
it says, the angel of the Lord turned to him and said,
Yeah, the Greeks booze it out.
Yeah, yeah.
At least there's two versions of Greek judges,
but we won't get into all that anyway.
But the point being that the angel of the Lord is closely identified with Yahweh here in this the whole Gideon story.
Right. The angel of Yahweh appears and then Yahweh turns its head to him, right?
And then Yahweh speaks again in verse 16 and then Gideon goes to get some food, right, to show hospitality.
and then it's the angel of Yahweh again, who's the actor, who extends his...
staff that he's carrying and touches it to the food that's sitting on a rock and the
food goes up in flames as a sacrifice as a burn offering. Right. And the smoke in flame
goes up to heaven and the angel of Yahweh disappears. When he disappears, Gideon's like, oh, no,
I'm going to die because he's seen God. Yeah. And then Yahweh who's apparently still there,
CREXITO it says no you're not gonna die.
You're okay.
Don't worry.
Do not fear you shall not die.
Now go destroy the locals' right and
to bail, but we won't continue the rest of that story until
another time.
Perhaps another day.
Yeah.
But so you see there, right, that once again,
there's this interchange as there was at the burning bush,
as we've seen until these other instances,
between the angel of Yahweh, who by virtue of being referred to
as the angel of Yahweh, the Yahweh angel,
is the
distinguished from Yahweh, but also is identified with Yahweh.
Yeah, God and God also God.
But there's only one God.
Yeah. Right.
Right. That's yeah.
And so now we're going to we're going to go into lightning round.
Yeah.
A whole lot of appearances.
Quick that that fast, but it's still us.
But we're just going to sort of cover briefly.
the other appearances and references to the angel of Yahweh in the Old Testament.
The first one, actually, as you're going through the Old Testament, is actually in Genesis 16,
the first person who encounters the angel of Yahweh in Scripture is actually Hegar.
The hand made of Sarah Abraham's wife, who is pregnant by this point with Abraham's son.
and has been cast out because she was just.
This is that hangar, not the one from Final.
fight, um, who became the mayor of town. Um, but not haggar the horrible. No, right. Um, so she's cast
out by Sarah and abused and the angel of Yahweh comes to her to strengthen her and care for her,
show her mercy and tell her that her son also is going to be the father of a mighty nation.
And it's going to be like a wild donkey, which is not recommended. If someone you know has a baby,
Right, go ahead and say it.
May your son be like a wild donkey of the desert.
Probably won't be taken as a blessing.
But in this case it was.
So the next one then is, and we talked about this scene a lot in our Abraham episode,
but this is the sacrifice of Isaac where you get the angel Lord speaks from heaven.
This is in Genesis 22 twice in verses 11 and 15.
And it says, again, the angel of Lord spoke to him, you know, stop, right?
Right. Right. Right. And this is not a case where there was a difference of opinion, right?
Like Yahweh wanted him to sacrifice Isaac and the angel of Yahweh didn't.
Yeah, no. Right. Right.
They are on the same page. Right. So the angel of Yahweh is here carrying out what Yahweh's intent was. Right.
right one with
one activity, right? So then we already alluded to this one, Numbers 22. This is
Balaum and his donkey. And there, here is where one of the places where the
Agile Viala appears with a drawn sword, standing between Balaum who's coming
to curse Israel and Israel, much the way the angels stood between the Egyptians.
right, and at Israel.
Yeah, and what's fun about this is that the scripture says it's the donkey that sees him.
Right. The donkey sees him and wants to turn back and Balaam is sort of beating the donkey trying to get it to stupid donkey.
Right. Balaam is actually mentioned in extra biblical inscriptions. He was sort of a Canaanite folk hero.
Baelumson of Bior.
A big deal.
Who was, he was this great prophet slash wizard slash sage type.
Yeah, and the scripture gives the vision of the uncreated God to the donkey and not to
Baileum.
Right.
So the idea is that the donkey, you know, it's your other word for donkey here, has more
wisdom and spiritual insight than the great prophet Baileum, right?
And then that leads to Baileum getting sent back by the angel when he finally sees him
to the king who hired him and then Balam does the thing.
where he tries to curse Israel and it ends up keep blessing Israel and there's this whole sort of
sitcom moment with the king. Stop blessing them. Yeah, I'm sorry. I'm trying. Yeah, I'm
Kim it or else she's got. Anyway, and just because people again love to hear me talk about this,
In Judges 13 before the birth of Samson,
Agile of Yahweh,
shows up to announce Samson's impending birth and tried to explain things to Samson's father.
And in their whole interchange between he and Samson's father, you really get glued
into how far gone Israel is at this point and how little understanding they have of the Torah and of the things of God.
Yeah, it's a weird, weird exchange where Samson's father, in particular, keeps wanting to worship
the angel of y'all.
in addition to Yahweh. Yeah right.
It makes his some other God in front of him.
Yeah and so the angel of Yahweh keeps saying
Yahweh is going to do this and he says,
okay but what's your name so we can worship you also
and sacrifice to you also?
It's like you're not getting this right?
I don't like. Yeah.
But this is the place where finally the angel of Yahweh
says why do you ask my name for?
It is wonderful.
It's wonderful.
Hmm.
Say, work.
Pay off from the first go.
Yeah, right.
So.
But yeah, so there's this whole
interchaid and they clearly,
and it's over and over and clearly
Samson's father doesn't get it.
You know, ends up naming him after
Shemesh, the pagan sun god.
Right.
That shows you that he never really gets it.
the second.
time after Genesis 16 with Haggar where the angel of Yahweh appears to announce an impending significant birth
Which is interesting in and of itself. Yeah
Yeah, so then there's another one where
The lesson the takeaway is don't take a census when you're not supposed to
Which should actually be your takeaway. Oh, okay. All right. Yeah
Yeah. Yeah, God sends a plague. That's sort of like the meaning of Genesis 3 is Don't Eat Fruit.
This is the part where I mentioned that the English word Apple was once a generic term that
meant fruit by the way. So it wasn't Apple. Just not necessarily a modern Apple. Yeah, okay, so
So yeah, there's two parallel accounts.
Second, Samuel 2416, first Chronicles 2116.
I'll read the second Samuel one. And when the angel stretched out his hand toward Jerusalem to destroy it,
the Lord relented from the calamity and said to the angel who was working destruction among the people,
it is enough now stay your hand. And the angel of the Lord was by the threshing floor of around the
the Jeb you site.
And it's a similar kind of thing in First Chronicles 2116,
and it's David in this case, seeing the info.
Lord and he has the drawn sword in his hand so forth.
Right. And the point of the thing with the census was that it was for taxation and military
recruitment.
Yeah.
Right.
And money and power.
And it represented a lack of trust in God, right, to go forth and fight the battles,
right?
Because it's like, no, I need more troops and I need more money.
Right.
Yeah.
rely on its own devices.
So then the angel of Yahweh appears and interacts with Elijah at a couple of points in first
kings or third kingdoms 19 and second kings or fourth kingdoms 1.
And what's interesting about those places is he comes and speaks with Elijah and it's
sort of paralleled in those same passages by the word of Yahweh coming to Elijah for shadowing.
Yeah, that'll be our setup.
be in our next episode everyone.
De Barrio, coming to Elijah and communicating with him.
And then there is good old second Kings 19 verse 35 and Isaiah 37 verse 36.
Yeah, where you get 185,000 data serians.
Yes, yes, which is a good start.
No, any.
These series were particularly wicked.
wicked and bloodthirsty. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So I mean, the context is that they've laid siege to Jerusalem
to come, you know, carry people off after destroying the northern kingdom. Right. Right.
Yeah. The Ted tribes end out there. They're after Jerusalem. And so there's this episode where they're
camped around Jerusalem. They're laying siege to it. They stop up the water as one does. They stop all
the food being brought in.
siege, right, to make them make them surrender after which they're going to do very, very horrible
things to all of them that we won't describe here because I made a promise that this would
be like last time. Anyway. Yeah. So, yeah. And so, sort of overnight, the Angel of Yahweh
goes through the camp and slaughters the Assyrian army. So they wake up in the morning, everybody's
that. Yeah, I mean, that's what it says. It says that night.
the angel Lord went out and struck down 185,000 of the camp of the serons.
When people rose early in the morning, behold, these were all dead bodies.
Yeah. So, now in the historical record, right, there's actually mention of this,
of the historical records I should say. So this isn't, you know, this isn't one that
to the local atheist usually goes after,
because there actually is...
them back up on this one that something happened. Right. Now they're going to come up with a very
naturalistic explanation of it. Right. Yeah. We're going to talk about what that is here in a second.
But because the the Assyrian records themselves, right, say that they went, they laid siege to
Jerusalem. And then they left. They left. Right. Right. Which the Syrians don't normally do that. Right.
like they don't start laying siege to a city and then just be like
and now
feeling it. Right. Right. And, and, you know, of course, in their own records, they're not going to say,
we suffered this humiliating defeat, and so we had to leave. No. Yeah, that's not what you
write into the history books. We return home victorious. Yeah, glorifying your people.
Right. Yeah. Yeah. There are, I mean, the Egyptians, the ancient Egyptians were especially bad at
there are battles where they lost huge numbers of troops and massive amounts
of territory.
and returned home victorious according to their own records.
Right.
So it's not different from our own day.
Yeah.
We won.
We totally won.
At worst it was a tie.
Right.
Yeah.
So, yeah.
And so in terms of other records.
So Josephus talks about this.
Josephus has come up a couple times today.
And Josephus says he's referring to Egyptian chronicles that he has access to because the
The big rivals of the Assyrians.
during that period were the Egyptians. The Egyptians were the other superpower during that period.
And so the Egyptian Chronicle, according to Josephus, indicates that rats entered the camp.
And the rats, Josephus, says, ate their bow strings.
Yeah, so they got up a weird detail, but there you go. Yeah. Now we've been dealing with church
which mice lately.
And they will eat through stuff, right?
But that would be kind of bizarre if they just all woke up and they're like, oh man, no
bowstrings.
Well, I guess we got to forget the siege.
It didn't bring any other weapons, right?
But what modern historians basically do with this is they say, well, wait a second, let's
think about this, right?
They blocked up the water sources.
They blocked up, that's in and out, right?
So basically
blocking up the sewers, they're blocking up the sources of fresh water, right?
Yeah, because that's what you do when you lay siege.
Right.
So what lives in the caves and tunnels and sewers under a city rats, right?
So if you stop them up, the rats aren't going to have food either.
They're going to come swarming out, right?
Through through holes and rats carry the plague.
Technically fleas on rats care the plague, but right.
Rats bring disease, right?
And so the
Generally accepted sort of secular explanation to this is that the Assyrians had to break the siege because there was a plague outbreak
in the camp
right
Now this is not
necessarily opposed to what the tech says
Right because
When we talked about second Samuel and we talked about first Chronicles where the angel of the Lord appeared with the drawn sword
That was in the context of a plague
Yeah
Striking Israel.
this could be referring to a plague, but just saying that that plague was not like an accident,
it was not a sort of natural occurrence, right? Because there were plenty of sieges that got laid
and there were no plague outbreaks, right? But that this was, that this plague outbreak was the
result of the angel of Yahweh coming to protect the people of God, because they repented and aligned
align themselves with God's will.
Yeah, the ancient sources are not in
compatible with each other. Right. Yeah. Right. Yeah. And so then finally, it's the big
tease for our next episode. The, well, there is briefly, if you look at Psalm 34, 7 and 35,
5 and 6 or 33 and 34, if you're in the Greek numbering, the angel of Yahweh is referred there
as camping about and protecting the righteous, right, defending the righteous. There's a sort of
military figure.
Yep. Yep. And then finally, here's this eggway, right? Zechariah chapter 1, the prophet Zechariah has this discussion with someone.
And so the question is, who is this person? Because in verse 7, this person is referred to as the word of Yahweh.
In verse 9 it's referred to as an angel.
In verse 10 it's referred to as a man.
and in verse 11 the same figure is referred to as the angel of Yahweh, the angel of the Lord.
And that's setting up our next few episodes. Indeed, indeed. So wow, we're going to do an
episode that might be just a hair over two hours. Can you believe it? Oh, I'm going to ramble.
Yeah, that's good. No, that's great. We can make up for the time. Yeah.
Right. So, okay, well, two...
to try to wrap this up, you know, again, this is a series. So we're not going to try to draw all possible conclusions.
But one of the things that I wanted to especially focus on, if you look at the angel of the Lord as depicted in Scripture,
he's often shown as being the one who is leading the armies of God and is protecting the people of Israel, sometimes punishing the people of Israel,
defeating God's enemy.
which is really good, especially when Israel is on board with him and is obeying him.
You see the aims of the Lord as we just heard about, you know, from the Assyrian siege,
being the one that's described as responsible for killing a lot of people, right?
You know, doing battle, right? This is the aims of the Lord.
This is the Son of God with a drawn sword.
That's not the only thing as we've heard.
that the angel of the Lord is associated with,
but it's a major, major element of the way
he's shown in Scripture.
And I think a lot of times when people see this
and we say, okay, this is Jesus, right?
You hear from Jude where he said
that Jesus saved the people of Israel from Egypt
as they were about to cross the Red Sea, right?
you know, and if you read in excess of teen...
that's described as God defeating those enemies, that God has done this. And so, you know,
not to allude too much to your book father, God is a man of war, but I mean, that's exactly where that
phrase comes from. And that describes in many ways the angel of the Lord, not the only way,
again, not the only way. But when people see this, if they're not used to looking at the whole
of Scripture and understanding that this is who this is.
and then they're told, okay, this is Jesus,
that can seem like a contradiction because,
at what point in the gospels does Jesus ever pick up a sword?
Right?
Well, no, Jesus is non-violence, Jesus,
this sort of thing.
And it can seem like this can't possibly be the same figure.
But one of the things that I think
it's really important to focus on
is that for these many centuries
that precede the gospels.
The age of the Lord is shown to be not a violent figure in the sense of like being aggressive
and wanting just to be the destroyer or whatever, but the one who is bringing God's justice,
the one who's making things right.
And so if we understand that that's who he is, and then he comes and he comes humbly,
very humbly.
not come is the son of a king, some earthly ruler, he does not come
You know with a whole bunch of you know with an army behind him
Right, he comes humbly and
offers himself
That's actually not a contradiction
Instead what you're getting is something much more powerful
You're seeing that the one who as he says he could command legions of angels
He says don't you know I could do this?
I mean he's making a reference to himself as the commander of the the hosts of the Lord
right when when he's being betrayed and arrested and so forth. This is don't you know I could call down legions of angels
Because that's who he is
Right that that one who can call down legions of angels and who has done that kind of thing before they know it
That's the one who offers himself
That's the one who
enters into a kind of
Special ops mission, so to speak right where the the
you get what's called the mess.
the oceanic secret that it's it's tricking the devil into the dark powers and to not realizing
what his mission is and utterly destroying and defeating them.
I've seen John Chrysostom says in his great homily, hell took a body and met God, right?
It was a, you know, like I said, special ops.
However you want to think of it.
But the point is is that that it's kept secret from the dark powers.
They don't understand what's going on.
And that's because of he came in humility.
Right, need to feed his enemies ultimately that way.
And then continuing on then, the Christ who is preached by the apostles and the Christ
whom we see especially in the apocalypse is, again, the Christ on his throne, the Christ
who is the command of the Lord's armies, the Christ who is establishing justice.
Right, if we understand that this is that Christ all the way through, then that makes the Jesus
whom we see in the gospels, it's much clearer than...
you know, what his suffering is about and what his sacrifice of himself is about, right?
It's not a contradiction. These aren't two different figures. This is the same one figure. Right?
And so he offers himself God in the flesh offers himself as a ransom to death, as a sacrifice, as purification for the whole world.
and only the one who is the angel of the Lord can do that.
only the one who is able to establish justice in the way that he does can do that.
And so to me looking at this is not dismaying at all.
It makes what we see in the gospels just so rich with meaning when you understand that
this is that Jesus, right?
And we're going to see more about, we're going to see more of this over the next few episodes.
But when you understand like what St. John says and the first, you know, the first chapter
of his gospel when he identifies.
this figure whom they've always known and says this is Jesus, that's big. That's really
big. And that's what's going on in the gospel. That's one of the things going on in the
gospels. And so this is just very, very powerful material for me. And I hope it has been for
everyone listening tonight as well. Father Stephen.
Yeah. So, as you mentioned, this is, this is the beginning of a series. And I think we've
you've already seen
even in this beginning, right, that when it comes to the Old Testament, it's not just angels on the sidelines puzzled and confused, but that Christ himself is actively involved.
And we're going to see him a lot of times when people talk about Christ and the Old Testament, you know, they think what you're going to do is you're going to say, every time there's a stick, oh, see that represents the cross.
and every time somebody is raised from the dead,
oh that's through.
resurrection of Christ, but that's not what we're talking about. We're talking about Christ himself
active in the Old Testament. And I think the
place where what we talked about tonight really rubs against
where we are and how we think as modern people
has to do with the very fact that this is Christ in the Old Testament. This is Christ active,
quote unquote.
before the incarnation entered into our human experience. Right?
Because it shows us that there's a reality that is far beyond
the day-to-day life that we experience.
And individualism, modern individualism is very attractive to our ego.
It's very attractive to our pride because what it does is,
it's sad.
whatever I'm dealing with today, whatever struggle I'm going through, whether
Pam go through whatever victory I'm experiencing, whatever success I have, that is the most
important thing in the universe. This is what is really happening and this is
what's really important. And so approaching things from that direction of
individualism can be very attractive. And it's not just our individual self and
our pure selfishness, but we've even in our modern world.
whittled down families from the huge extended families and households that existed for most of human history to little nuclear families, if that, and even that now is starting to break apart into collections of individuals.
And we see societies and communities
as collections of individuals, even church parishes.
Individuals come, they experience the services,
and then they leave.
Right.
as individuals at Go Home having received, they hope what they were looking for when they came.
When if we look at it from the other perspective, from the perspective that's required by what
we've been talking about tonight, that there is an eternal reality that is being worked out that
we're beginning to experience now, that's beginning to enter into our experience now, but that is
is the most real.
That takes all of these things we experience on a day to day basis, both good and bad and
relativizes them.
That takes a hit to our ego.
My anxiety is not the most important thing in the universe.
My success at something is not the most important thing in the universe.
Christ is the center of what's going on in the universe at all times.
But what this means positively, beyond just, hey, don't worry, be happy, right?
is that, for example, when we think about St. Gregory the
theologian, if you read a lot of St. Gregory the theologian,
you'll find that he spends a lot of time talking about his
irritable bowel syndrome, at least that's what we'd call it
today. That may shocks of people, but it's absolutely true
read his letters. He wrote prayers to God that he said when
he was experiencing this pain and distress and suffering.
It's very human.
That's not how we use...
think about St. Gregory and the theologian. The the the himnography as far as I know
someone can correct me but I'm pretty sure the himnography is his feast and the
feast of the three holy hierarchs does not mention his health problems at all.
The St. Gregory who appears to us in the in the services who we come to know
through the services and through reading his writings preserved in the church
is sort of a different St. Gregory than.
that, right? And it's not that that's not the real St. Gregory. We've been taught by our 19th century
German friends to think, well, the person who if I got in a Tartus and went back to the 4th century
and met Gregory, if I met that person, that person with the suffering and the bathroom problems
and all that stuff, that's the real Gregory. And this other thing is this Artifice of the Church,
this invented thing, this legend
that doesn't have reality to it.
And that's getting it exactly backwards.
The real Saint Gregory is the Saint Gregory in the church.
The real Saint Gregory is that Saint Gregory who we come to know,
because that's who Saint Gregory is in eternity.
That's who Saint Gregory is at the end of his journey.
That's who Saint Gregory became.
game. The holy one who he became.
And the same is true, at least in potency for each of us.
Right? The experiences we have, the struggles we go through,
this victories, the failures, everything we go through in this life,
is the reality of who we are in Christ entering into our experience,
gradually, because we're human and we're finite and we're flawed,
and that's how we have to process it, a second and a bit, and a piece at a time,
to try to grow.
and change into the likeness of Christ.
And so that means that who I am in Christ is the ultimate reality of myself.
Not how messed up I may feel about myself, not how horrible I may feel about myself,
not whatever the little voice in the back of my head is telling me is true about
myself because that little voice isn't me as we talked about in a previous
episode, right? None of that is who I am. Who I am in Christ is something that
It stands out before me.
and that I'm working toward and coming to experience bit by bit and piece by piece
and hoping to to eventually become fully in the age to come.
And I think if we approach not just our own lives that way,
but when we approach others in our community and our family and our parishes,
not as who they may be right now when I encounter them with all their flaws
and other difficulties and other good qualities.
Right? But is the person who they are in Christ, the person who they're coming to be,
and understand that we can have the joy of experiencing that with them.
Then that will transform everything for us, for our communities, for the life of those communities.
Because it's not just us, it's our families who could become what our family was created to be.
It's our parishes can become what our parishes were created to be in Christ, our communities,
all the way up right
to the whole inhabited world can become in Christ what they were created to be.
And I think to do that, we have to keep our eyes not on the day-to-day struggle, the moment-to-moment
pluses and minuses rejoicing in the momentary victories and mourning the momentary failures.
But keeping our eyes focused on eternity and on Christ too dwells there.
Amen. That's a good word.
Well, that is our show for tonight.
Thank you very much, everyone, for listening.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during the live broadcast,
we'd love to hear from you, either via email at Lord of Spirits
at ancientfaith.com or you can message us
at our Lord of Spirits podcast, Facebook page.
We do read everything, but we can't respond to everything.
And we do save some of what you send
for possible use in future episodes.
Join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays
of the month at 7 PM Eastern 4 PM Pacific.
If you're on Facebook, like our page, join our
discussion group, leave reviews and ratings everywhere, but most importantly share this show
with a friend whom you know is gonna love it.
Really you should get off social media.
And instead go to achiffaith.com, stroke support, and help make sure we and lots of other
AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much.
Good night, and God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice,
worthy is the land that was slain to receive
p-